<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Justin Chan</title>
    <link>https://justinchan.one/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Justin Chan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 17:41:57 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://justinchan.one/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Going from Java to Python: the Good, the Surprising, and the Bad</title>
      <link>https://justinchan.one/posts/java-to-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 17:41:57 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justinchan.one/posts/java-to-python/</guid>
      <description>7 months ago I joined Lyft from Salesforce. It’s been interesting seeing the differences in the two companies’ tech stacks, tooling and culture. Now that I’ve completed several projects, I feel somewhat equipped to share my two cents on working in a Java vs. Python codebase. It’s certainly not an apples to apples comparison, as a developer’s experience is affected by many factors including infrastructure, tech debt, company culture, and the specific framework and libraries used1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>https://justinchan.one/posts/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 09:09:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justinchan.one/posts/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m starting this site to encourage myself to reflect and think through things more deeply, something I think is important in a world that gravitates towards sound bites and reductionism. There&amp;rsquo;ll be posts on my interests, current events, books I&amp;rsquo;ve read, life experiences, and questions I find interesting.
It&amp;rsquo;ll also be a record of sorts for myself. Past photos and videos are great for reliving highs and lows, but don&amp;rsquo;t quite capture our thoughts at a particular moment in time in high resolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Questions</title>
      <link>https://justinchan.one/questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 12:01:35 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justinchan.one/questions/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of questions that I enjoy reading about and discussing. Some of these subjects I know very little about, so any opinions or suggestions on relevant reading would be appreciated.
Technology
  How can we mitigate bias in predictive models, especially those in fields with material consequences like credit, criminal justice, university admissions, and hiring?
  Is it only a matter of time before software engineering becomes commoditized?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://justinchan.one/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 19:55:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justinchan.one/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m currently a software engineer at Lyft, working on making the platform safer between users.
I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing about things that interest me. Broadly speaking, that includes tech, software, economics, sports and sociology. Another way to frame my interests are these questions.
In my free time, I enjoy reading, listening to music, and all things sports (badminton, soccer and more recently, running). I like figuring out, reasoning about, building and improving systems.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>